# 爆点在哪儿呢 健康
What makes this dish extraordinary? - Healthy.
# 越滚越白 越黏了
It’s boiled white and dense.
# 操作当中的最爆点在哪儿 简单
What is the best part while cooking this dish? - Simple.
# 过去就在这勺子上就弄上了
# 注释：存疑
Traditionally you can even operate with an spoon.
# 您能气死我
You piss me off, Sir!
# 您说啊
Then, what's your comment?
# 家家都能做
Everyone can cook it at home.
# 米汤浸时蔬
Rice Soup & Veggie Stew
# 这是卫青萝卜
This is Weiqin Radish.
# 先把这个萝卜给它刮下皮
First peel the skin.
# 青萝卜白萝卜都行是吧
Green radish and white radish both work, right?
# 咱们用青萝卜是为了颜色好看一点
We use green ones only for atheistic purpose.
# 食材都比较普通  家家都有
These are common ingredients.
# 辛苦您帮我坐点水 好
Would you boil some water for me? Sure.
# 切成萝卜丝
Julienne the radish.
# 咱们这萝卜丝切好了
Our radish julienne are ready.
# 然后咱们水里边下几个花椒粒
Drop a couple of SiChuan Peppercorns.
# 作用是去掉萝卜的臭萝卜味儿
This step should eliminate the “Radish Odor”.
# 够了吧 够了 再多了有味儿了
Good? Good, we don’t want the pungent taste.
# 这行了关火 你看这米油 没问题了
Alright turn off the heat. It’s all set, the rice soup oozes out.
# 粥底的一个做法
Here’s one of the method to prepare the congee base.
# 广东菜就用米汤浸时蔬
Guangdong Dish boils veggies in rice soup.
# 浸好多菜 都是用这种方法做的
(Rice soup) is good company for many veggies, all using the same method.
# 后来给演绎过来了
Then we have this kind of dish as successor.
# 水开了 咱把萝卜丝下锅焯一下
The water ‘s boiling, blanch the radish julienne.
# 去掉萝卜的臭气味
Get rid of the radish odor.
# 放点盐 增加点底味
Add a grin of salt to enhance the flavor.
# 可以把花椒撇出来了
Fish out the peppercorns.
# 比如说老年人可以把萝卜炖的烂糊点
You can cook the radish to well done for your elders to enjoy.
# 这样入口即化
This way it melts into your mouth.
# 再有还可以配点金针菇啊
And you can also get some Enokitake mushroom.
# 这种丝状的蘑菇
This kind of mushrooms.
# 虾丸鱼片这都行 因为萝卜吃腥
# 注释：check afterwards
Shrimp balls, fish fillet are all good choices. Radish can balance their fishy odor.
# 大爷 虾最好用什么虾好吃啊
Da Ye, what kind of shrimp tastes the best?
# 生敲 生敲虾片
Shredded prawn slices.
# 吃着滑爽再搁这粥里边
The smooth texture of prawn makes it a good addition for congee.
# 虾球 虾片 鱼丸 这都行
Shrimp balls, shredded prawn, fish balls, all good.
# 你闻闻大爷这气味
Da Ye, smell it.
# 清香青脆 颜色好看
It’s faintly fragrant and crispy, the color also looks nice.
# 咱们把这水倒了
Let’s pour out the water.
# 把米油过滤出来
Filter out the rice soup.
# 咱把火点上 它得调味儿
Turn on the heat, we need to season it.
# 瑶柱 瑶柱水 做好的（提前泡）
Dried scallops and scallops water. We soaked the scallops in advance.
# 倒在米油里边
Pour it into the rice oil.
# 你看这个米汤很匀称 比勾芡还勾的好
You can tell that the texture of the rice soup is perfectly uniform, better than adding slurry.
# 瑶柱这香味马上就出来了 鲜味出来了
Scallops’ savory aroma comes out immediately.
# 马上调味
Season it right now.
# 盐 少搁点盐
Salt, add a little bit of salt.
# 然后（白）胡椒粉
After that, add white pepper.
# （白）胡椒粉提鲜
White pepper can boost the umami flavor.
# 然后点一点糖代替味精 有一点就行 提鲜
Add a touch of sugar instead of SMG, just a bit, for the umami flavor.
# 越滚越白 越黏了 收汁
The soup is boiled white and dense, reduce the liquid.
# 这个孕妇确实吃这不错
This dish is pretty good for pregnant women.
# 好 咱们把火关了
Alright, let’s turn off the heat.
# 过去就在这勺子上就弄上了
In the past we do this step with a spoon
# 好了师父 够了 家常方法
Alright Master, we have sufficient techniques for home cooking already~
# 咱们来点干贝 揉碎
Crush some dried scallops.
# 咱们撒在上边 星星点点
We sprinkle the crush on it.
# 好了 别太多了
Enough, don’t add too much
# 来大爷 您先尝尝
Da Ye, try it first.
# 听这声音还是不错
According to the sound made—it’s not bad.
# 清爽   细腻
Refreshing, smooth and delicate.
# 为什么细腻 这米汤你看 不澥
Why smooth? Look at the soup, it’s not watery.
# 真好喝
Taste great!
# 爆点在哪儿呢 健康
What makes this dish extraordinary? - Healthy
# 最爆点 操作当中的最爆点
What is the best part while cooking this dish?
# 简单
Simple.
# 您能气死我
You pissed me off, Sir!
# 您说
Then, what's your comment?
# 这个点在哪呢
What is important?
# 大爷 你看她那花椒加的特别巧
Da Ye, she added peppercorns with very intricate techniques.
# 你看一点花椒味儿吃不出来
There are barely any peppercorns’ pungency at all.
# 而且把萝卜这味给带走了
It balances the radish taste as well.
# 这就是亮点 亮点在这儿
This is the key, it’s right here.
# 其实呢原来也有自己的一个愿望
Actually, I used to have a dream.
# 我想呢 这辈子干点什么呢
I thought to myself, what did I want to do with my life.
# 第一
Initially,
# 没想干厨师啊
I did not desire to be a chef.
# 想当个裁缝
I wanted to be a tailor.
# 因为我觉得裁缝是个手艺人
Because I thought a tailor would be a handicraftsman.
# 一把剪子
A scissor.
# 不同的布料能裁出各种的
And varying clothing are made...
# 千变万化的服装
...from different materials.
# 因为我小时候也爱穿新衣服
I loved new clothes when I was a kid.
# 所以就想当个裁缝
That also made me want to be a tailor.
# 这个愿望没实现
This dream never comes true.
# 第二个愿望想当一个
My second dream drove me to be a...
# 那叫文秘
...As it was called, a secretarial clerk.
# 现在叫秘书
Now we just call it Secretary.
# 我就想呢写个报告啊 写个什么东西
All I wanted was to write a report or something.
# 那阵也没有电脑
Back then there was no computer.
# 全是那种铅印的打印机
Those letterpress typewriters occupied the entire market.
# 凿那个铅字的
Carving the lead characters...
# 刷那油墨的
Or brushing ink onto the printer.
# 我说我要把字练好了
I told myself I was gonna try hard on practicing calligraphy. (The art of writing beautiful Chinese Characters)
# 我给领导写篇文章
Then I might write an article for the leadership.
# 写个总结 写个报告
Or I could write a summary, a report.
# 所以那阵我从上中学的时候
Hence since I was in middle school.
# 我抄过王杰日记
I tried to transcribe the Diary of Wang Jie,
# 欧阳海日记
The Diary of Ou Yang Hai,
# 焦裕禄日记
The Diary of Jiao Yu Lu.
# 你看我的作业
Take a look at my homework,
# 就上中学的数学作业
Middle school math homework to be specific.
# 我从来不用铅笔
I never use pencils.
# 我的作业全部都是钢笔
My homework’s were all written with pens.
# 而且写语文我这个作业本上没有一个是改过的
And while writing my Chinese homework I never did change a single character on my notebook.
# 只要我写错了一个字
As soon as I wrote even one character wrong,
# 这张纸就撕了
I tore the sheet of paper.
# 最挠头的时候
At the most head-scratching moment,
# 最后一行写错了两个字
I miswrote two characters in the last row.
# 但是我不涂不改
But I did not obliterate on the spots.
# 撕 重新写
Tore it! Wrote it all over again.
# 希望我们的网友呢
I hope our dear viewers.
# 需要哪方面的知识
Don’t hesitate to leave a massage,
# 都提示给我
If you need any information from us.
# 我通过老饭骨的叨叨叨
I hope to understand what our viewers want...
# 来了解大家的需求
...by keeping nagging at you on Lao Fangu.
# 尽量满足大家的愿望
We will be trying our best to meet your expectations,
# 分享这方面的知识
To share knowledge of such.
# 我们一定跟您好好学
We will definitely learn from you!
# 今天咱们就聊到这
Let’s call it a day.
# 谢谢小语
Thank you! Xiao Yu.